Gitís patches are much like RTCís change sets. Both systems have workspace areas locally and remotely, with separate actions required to move code from your workspace to a common delivery area



    A Git Commit is called Delivering in RTC
    A Git repository is now a Stream
    A Branch is loosely a workspace. One can create many workspaces where one can
    Git tag is essentially a baseline in RTC; however one must accept these baselines in your code otherwise you will have merge conflicts

GIT		RTC
Snapshot	Changeset
Snapshot is being used here as a layman's synonym for a commit. A commit object is essentially metadata (author, date, message) and a snapshot of the contents of your work tree (represented as a tree object)

your local repository consists of three "trees" maintained by git. the first one is your Working Directory which holds the actual files. the second one is the Index which acts as a staging area and finally the HEAD which points to the last commit you've made

You can propose changes (add it to the Index) using git add filename

git commit -m "Commit message" - Now the file is committed to the HEAD, but not in your remote repository yet.

Your changes are now in the HEAD of your local working copy. To send those changes to your remote repository, execute
git push origin master



Branches are used to develop features isolated from each other. The master branch is the "default" branch when you create a repository.


create a new branch named "feature_x" and switch to it using
git checkout -b feature_x


to update your local repository to the newest commit, execute
git pull


to merge another branch into your active branch (e.g. master), use
git merge <branch>


In a DistributedVCS
(such as Git, Mercurial, Bazaar or Darcs), clients donít just check out the latest snapshot of the files: they fully mirror the repository



(CVS, Subversion,
Perforce, Bazaar, and so on) think of the information they keep as a set of
files and the changes made to each file over time.
Git thinks of its data
more like a set of snapshots of a miniature filesystem. Every time you commit,
or save the state of your project in Git, it basically takes a picture of what all
your files look like at that moment and stores a reference to that snapshot.To
be efficient, if files have not changed, Git doesnít store the file again, just a link
to the previous identical file it has already stored. Git thinks about its data more
like a stream of snapshots.


The Git directory is where Git stores the metadata and object database for
your project


The working directory is a single checkout of one version of the project.
These files are pulled out of the compressed database in the Git directory and
placed on disk for you to use or modify.


The staging area is a file, generally contained in your Git directory, that
stores information about what will go into your next commit


You do a commit, which takes the files as they are in the staging area and
stores that snapshot permanently to your Git directory


You can get a Git project using two main approaches. The first takes an existing
project or directory and imports it into Git. The second clones an existing Git
repository from another server.


If you commit at this point, the version of the file at the time you
ran git add is what will be in the historical snapshot.


git add is a multipurpose command ñ you use it to begin tracking
new files, to stage files, and to do other things like marking merge-conflicted
files as resolved
If you modify a file after you run git add, you have
to run git add again to stage the latest version of the file



The rules for the patterns you can put in the .gitignore file are as follows:
ï Blank lines or lines starting with # are ignored.
ï Standard glob patterns work.
ï You can start patterns with a forward slash (/) to avoid recursivity.
ï You can end patterns with a forward slash (/) to specify a directory.
ï You can negate a pattern by starting it with an exclamation point (!).


git diff
That command compares what is in your working directory with what is in
your staging area
git diff --staged
This command compares your staged changes
to your last commit:


git commit -a -m 'added new benchmarks' skip staging.-a flag includes all changed
files. 



To remove a file from Git, you have to remove it from your tracked files (more
accurately, remove it from your staging area) and then commit
rm PROJECTS.md
git rm PROJECTS.md



git rm --cached README
you may want to
keep the file on your hard drive but not have Git track it anymore. This is particularly
useful if you forgot to add something to your .gitignore file and accidentally
staged it


git mv file_from file_to
rename file



git reset HEAD CONTRIBUTING.md
unstage file


Unmodifying a Modified File
git checkout -- CONTRIBUTING.md



Remote repositories are versions of your project that
are hosted on the Internet or network somewhere. You can have several of
them, each of which generally is either read-only or read/write for you




git remote
To see which remote servers you have configured


If
youíve cloned your repository, you should at least see origin ñ that is the default
name Git gives to the server you cloned from



git remote -v
shows you the URLs that Git has stored for the
shortname to be used when reading and writing to that remote



git fetch [remote-name]
to get data from your remote projects


git fetch origin fetches any new
work that has been pushed to that server since you cloned
git fetch command only downloads
the data to your local repository ñ it doesnít automatically merge it with any of
your work or modify what youíre currently working on. You have to merge it
manually into your work when youíre ready

use the git pull command
to automatically fetch and then merge that remote branch into your current
branch



git push [remote-name][branch-name]
git push origin master




If you and someone
else clone at the same time and they push upstream and then you push upstream,
your push will rightly be rejected. Youíll have to fetch their work first
and incorporate it into yours before youíll be allowed to push


git remote show origin
shows which branch is automatically pushed to when you
run git push while on certain branches



by
default, the git clone command automatically sets up your local master
branch to track the remote master branch (or whatever the default branch is
called) on the server you cloned from.


branching
In many VCS tools, this is a somewhat expensive
process, often requiring you to create a new copy of your source code directory,



Git doesnít store data as a series of
changesets or differences, but instead as a series of snapshots



When you make a commit, Git stores a commit object that contains a pointer
to the snapshot of the content you staged. This object also contains the authorís
name and email, the message that you typed, and pointers to the commit


Staging the files checksums each one
(the SHA-1 hash we mentioned in Chapter 1), stores that version of the file in the Git repository (Git refers to them as blobs), and adds that checksum to the
staging area:


Your Git repository now contains five objects: one blob for the contents of
each of your three files, one tree that lists the contents of the directory and
specifies which file names are stored as which blobs, and one commit with the
pointer to that root tree and all the commit metadata.


FIGURE 3-2
Commits and their
parents



A branch in Git is simply a lightweight movable pointer to one of these commits.



How does Git know what branch youíre currently on? It keeps a special
pointer called HEAD.
The git branch command only created a new branch ñ it didnít switch to that
branch.


FIGURE 3-5


git checkout testing
To switch to an existing branch
This moves HEAD to point to the testing branch



SWITCHING BRANCHES CHANGES FILES IN YOUR WORKING
DIRECTORY
If you switch to an older branch, your
working directory will be reverted to look like it did the last time you
committed on that branch. If Git cannot do it cleanly, it will not let you
switch at all.




Because a branch in Git is in actuality a simple file that contains the 40 character
SHA-1 checksum of the commit it points to, branches are cheap to create
and destroy. Creating a new branch is as quick and simple as writing 41 bytes to
a file (40 characters and a newline).
This is in sharp contrast to the way most older VCS tools branch, which involves
copying all of the projectís files into a second directory.


git checkout master
git merge hotfix
--now master and hotfix are pointing to latest version


git branch -d hotfix
deleting hotfix branch


Because the
commit on the branch youíre on isnít a direct ancestor of the branch youíre
merging in, Git has to do some work. In this case, Git does a simple three-way merge **
This is referred to as a merge commit, and is special in
that it has more than one parent



Itís worth pointing out that Git determines the best common ancestor to use
for its merge base; this is different than older tools like CVS or Subversion (before
version 1.5), where the developer doing the merge had to figure out the
best merge base for themselves



After youíve resolved each of
these sections in each conflicted file, run git add on each file to mark it as resolved.
Staging the file marks it as resolved in Git



graphical tool 
git mergetool


While ìmasterî is the default name for a
starting branch when you run git init which is the only reason itís
widely used, ìoriginî is the default name for a remote when you run git
clone.




Remote-tracking branches
act as bookmarks to remind you where the branches in your remote repositories
were the last time you connected to them.


FIGURE 3-22
Server and local
repositories after
cloning


FIGURE 3-23
Local and remote
work can diverge


FIGURE 3-24
git fetch updates
your remote
references


when we pull an repo, we will have 2 pointers in local...origin/master and master


git push <remote> <branch>
git push origin serverfix



Tracking branches are local branches that have a direct relationship
to a remote branch
If youíre on a tracking branch and type git
pull, Git automatically knows which server to fetch from and branch to merge
into



While the git fetch command will fetch down all the changes on the server
that you donít have yet, it will not modify your working directory at all. It will
simply get the data for you and let you merge it yourself. However, there is a
command called git pull which is essentially a git fetch immediately followed
by a git merge in most cases


git push origin --delete serverfix



In Git, there are two main ways to integrate changes from one branch into another:
the merge and the rebase


There is no difference in the end product
of the integration, but rebasing makes for a cleaner history



Although you can technically push changes to
and pull changes from individualsí repositories, doing so is discouraged because
you can fairly easily confuse what theyíre working on if youíre not careful.



A remote repository is generally a bare repository ñ a Git repository that has
no working directory.
In the simplest terms, a bare repository is the contents of your
projectís .git directory and nothing else


In fact, for services like GitHub, the URL you use to view the repository online
(for example, ìhttps://github.com/schacon/simplegitî) is the same URL you
can use to clone and, if you have access, push over


If you want to contribute to an existing project to which you donít have push
access, you can ìforkî the project. What this means is that GitHub will make a
copy of the project that is entirely yours; it lives in your userís namespace, and
you can push to it


The GitHub Flow
GitHub is designed around a particular collaboration workflow, centered on
Pull Requests



Forking is nothing more than a clone on the GitHub server side:

without the possibility to directly push back
with fork queue feature added to manage the merge request
So by definition, you cannot fork a branch



A file in the working tree of a Git repository can have different states. These states are the following:

untracked: the file is not tracked by the Git repository. This means that the file never staged nor committed.

tracked: committed and not staged

staged: staged to be included in the next commit

dirty / modified: the file has changed but the change is not staged



Use git rm instead of just rm
Use git mv instead of just mv



A clone can be considered a full backup of all the data in your remote repository, but not necessarily the meta-data (that's where the --mirror switch comes in). Your clone will contain all the commit, tree, blob, branch, and tag objects that are in any way referenced by the repository. That means your backup will contain all your source code, history, and associated branches or tags.


http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/Git/article.html

DVCS
Typically, there is a central server for keeping a repository but each cloned repository is a full copy of this repository. The decision which of the copies is considered to be the central server repository is pure convention.
A local non-bare Git repository is typically called local repository.



You can use ^ (caret) and ~ (tilde) to reference predecessor commit objects from other references. You can also combine the ^ and ~ operators. See Using caret and tilde for commit references for their usage.

The Git terminology is parent for ^ and ancestor for ~



Instead of writing a tool that versions each file individually, like Subversion, we would probably write one that makes it easier to store snapshots of our project without having to copy the whole directory each time.
This is essentially what Git is. You tell Git you want to save a snapshot of your project with the git commit command and it basically records a manifest of what all of the files in your project look like at that point.





There are two main ways to get a Git repository. One way is to simply initialize a new one from an existing directory, such as a new project or a project new to source control. The second way is to clone one from a public Git repository





n important concept here is that Git has an 'index', which acts as sort of a staging area for your snapshot. This allows you to build up a series of well composed snapshots from changed files in your working directory, rather than having to commit all of the file changes at once.


git diff HEAD 		show diff of all staged or unstaged changes
If you want to see both staged and unstaged changes together, you can run git diff HEAD - this basically means you want to see the difference between your working directory and the last commit, ignoring the staging area



staged the content - git add command, 
you run git commit to actually record the snapshot.





git reset HEAD - what you are actually doing is git reset HEAD --mixed and it will "reset" the index to the state it was before you started adding files / adding modifications to the index ( via git add ) In this case, the working copy and the index ( or staging ) were in sync, but you made the HEAD and the index to be in sync after the reset.

git rm on the other hand removes a file from the working directory and the index and when you commit, the file is removed from the tree as well.


****
http://stackoverflow.com/questions/8198105/how-does-git-store-files
